AMLAN SINHA

Ŷ 297 Franklin Ave, Princeton, NJ ■ amlans@princeton.edu □ (929) · 428 · 6138

RESEARCH STATEMENT

I am a Ph.D. candidate in Mechanical and Aerospace Engineering at Princeton University, specializing in dynamical systems, optimal control and astrodynamics. My research aims to harness knowledge from dynamical systems and optimal control to develop a theoretical and algorithmic framework to design robust trajectories for low-thrust spacecrafts under operational uncertainty such as partial or complete engine loss in complex multibody dynamical systems during the preliminary mission design phase.

Research Interests: Astrodynamics, Dynamical Systems, Optimal Control, Robust Control

EDUCATION

2020-Present Princeton University

Doctoral Candidate in Mechanical Engineering

Certificates: Computational Science and Engineering

Princeton University May 2020

M.A. in Mechanical Engineering

GPA: 3.61/4.00

Cornell University May 2018

B.S. in Mechanical Engineering, Minor in Aerospace Engineering

GPA: 3.52/4.00 (Cum Laude)

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Beeson Lab Jan 2022 - Present Princeton, NJ

Graduate Research Assistant, Adviser: Ryne Beeson

- · Quantitatively and qualitatively assess the role of dynamical structures on robust low-thrust spacecraft trajectories in complex multibody dynamical environments,
- · Investigate the structure of optimal solutions for low-thrust non-robust spacecraft trajectories in complex multibody dynamical environments from a global optimization perspective

Rowley Lab Aug 2018 - Dec 2021 Graduate Research Assistant Princeton, NJ

· Developed a Bayesian algorithm to determine optimal control strategies minimizing the worst-case regret for a linear dynamical system with an unknown system parameter with additive gaussian noise.

CONFERENCE PUBLICATIONS

Olson, A., Sinha, A., Chhabra, A., Fry, S., Ahner, K., Beeson, R. (2024) "A Feasibility Study of Microsat Mission Architectures for Ring Science in the Uranian System" AAS/AIAA Space Flight Mechanics Conference, American Astronautical Society, Orlando, FL.

Sinha, A., Beeson, R. (2023) "On Robust Low Thrust Trajectories and Invariant Manifolds" AAS/AIAA Space Flight Mechanics Conference, American Astronautical Society, Big Sky, MT.

Sinha, A., Beeson, R. (2023) "Analysis of Robust Low Thrust Trajectories For The Lunar Gateway" AAS/AIAA Space Flight Mechanics Conference, American Astronautical Society, Big Sky, MT.

Li, A., Sinha, A., Beeson, R. (2023) "Amortized Global Search for Efficient Preliminary Trajectory Design with Deep Generative Models" AAS/AIAA Space Flight Mechanics Conference, American Astronautical Society, Big Sky, MT.

Beeson, R., Sinha, A., Jagannatha, B., Bunce, D., and Carroll, D. (2022) "Dynamically Leveraged Automated Multibody (N) Trajectory Optimization," AAS/AIAA Space Flight Mechanics Conference, American Astronautical Society, Charlotte, NC.

Soto, G., Sinha, A., Savransky, D., Delacroix, C., Garrett, D. (2017) "Starshade orbital maneuver study for WFIRST." SPIE Proc. Techniques and Instrumentation for Detection of Exoplanets VIII

Soto, G., Lloyd, J., Savransky, D., Grogan, K., Sinha, A. (2017) "Optimization of high-inclination orbits using planetary flybys for a zodiacal light-imaging mission." SPIE Proc. Techniques and Instrumentation for Detection of Exoplanets VIII

JOURNAL PUBLICATIONS

Sinha, A., Eggl, M., Fefferman, C., Rowley, C.W. (in preparation) "Optimal control for a scalar linear dynamical system with unknown parameter."

FELLOWSHIPS, AWARDS AND HONORS

C.V. Starr Fellowship, Merit Fellowship, Princeton University (2020)

\$95,000

Graduate Teaching Fellowship, Merit Fellowship, Princeton University (2020)

N/A

University Administrative Fellowship, Professional Development Fellowship, Princeton University (2019)

\$1,000

Engineering Learning Initiative, Summer Research Fellowship, Cornell University (2015-17)

\$12,000

Cornell University Scholarship, Full-Ride Undergraduate Scholarship, Cornell University (2014-18)

\$320,000

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Graduate Teaching Assistant

2018-Present

 $Princeton\ University$

Princeton, NJ

- · MAE 206 (Engineering Dynamics)
- · MAE 342 (Space Systems Design)
- · MAE 433 (Automatic Control Systems)
- · MAE 501 (Mathematical Methods of Engineering Analysis)

Undergraduate Teaching Assistant

2014-2018

Cornell University

Ithaca, NY

- · ENGRG 1112 (Practical Computing in Engineering)
- · MAE 2210 (Thermodynamics)
- · MAE 2030 (Engineering Dynamics)
- · MAE 3260 (System Dynamics)

OUTREACH AND LEADERSHIP EXPERIENCE

Garden State Youth Correctional Facility, Crosswicks, NJ

Aug 2021-Present

Instructor (Math): Developed a course for 15 incarcerated youth, arranged 2 workshops to discuss post-graduation career opportunities in STEM, designed multiple team-building activities in collaboration with 50+ volunteers

McGraw Center For Teaching and Learning, Princeton, NJ

Aug 2021-Present

Associate-in-Instruction Training Facilitator: Provided training to 25+ new graduate teaching assistants, led 3 teaching pedagogy workshops, and designed 10+ team-building activities to foster community and enhance teaching skills.

Start Smart (a summer program for low-income students from Bangladesh)

May 2020-Present

Co-Founder: Found a non-profit focused on educational advancement, provided college application support for 250+ low-income high school students from Bangladesh securing a cumulative total of \$1 million in financial aid, planned 10+ networking events with industry professionals

Graduate Student Committe (MAE), Princeton, NJ

Jan 2020-July 2021

Sustainability Chair: Served as liaison between department and graduate school adovcating for environmentally conscious practices (reducing annual energy consumption by 5%), managed programming for 3 sustainability focused events, wrote bi-weekly newsletters to 250+ students and faculty members

RELEVANT COURSEWORK

Classical Mechanics, Dynamical Systems, Optimal Control, Numerical Analysis, Linear Programming, Convex Optimization, Machine Learning

TECHNICAL STRENGTHS

Computer Languages

Python, C, C++, Matlab

Tools

Bash, Git, Latex, Mathematica, Jira

Design and Fabrication

Solidworks, ANSYS, Arduino, Raspberry Pi

Research Skills

Classical Mechanics, Dynamical Systems, Optimal Control, Optimization, High Performance Computing, Model Reduction, Time-Series Analysis